Alex Shulaev

Software Engineering Manager | Frontend Lead

Location: Armenia, Yerevan Mobile: +374 55 44 7107 Email: <u>alexandrshy@gmail.com</u>

Telegram: @alexandrshy

LinkedIn: <u>linkedin.com/in/alexandrshy</u> GitHub: <u>github.com/Alexandrshy</u>

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Front End Engineer with eight years of experience in various teams. My main working principle: the interface must solve business problems and be user friendly. Lately I have also focused on technical management. I want to share my knowledge and solve more global problems.

SKILLS

Technical skills

JavaScript, TypeScript, HTML, CSS, React, Redux, Jest, React Testing Library, Node.js, styled-components, PostCSS, webpack, Svelte, ESLint, Prettier

Management skills

Mentoring, People Management, Team Building, Team Management, Business Process Improvement, Forming and supporting a community

WORK EXPERIENCE

Optimax Dev | Software Engineering Manager Aug 2018 - Jan 2022 | Remote work

- Improved and documented the onboarding process for new developers, the decision-making process within teams, and the one-on-one meeting process. This increased developer retention at the company without increasing the budget.
- Prepared a roadmap for developers who want to move into the role of team leader. This accelerated the search for new engineering leaders internally and in hiring.
- Developed and implemented the MVP for the design system. React + Styled Components stack and CI/CD based on GitHub actions were chosen for the system. Implemented automatic documentation of releases based on commit messages using semantic-release.

Optimax Dev | Engineering Lead

Dec 2019 - Jan 2022 | Remote work

- Engineering lead for the Analytics team, which collects and provides the Data team with all the information on user actions and preferences.
- Successfully proved to be an Engineering lead and after the Analytics team was ready to manage without me I moved to organize a new team - Product Labs, which dealt with A/B testing and personalization of user experience.
- Implemented a modal window widget using the Module Federation in webpack. This solution allowed to take some of the code out of the main bundle and load it delayed. It allowed to improve loading speed of the site
- Implemented a new tool for displaying unique recommendations for clients. This increased conversion rates by 15% for returning users.
- Conducted global refactoring of critical experiments. As a result, the size of the experiment package was reduced by 30%, and the time required to load an experiment was reduced by 40%.
- Added metrics to collect information on Web Vitals metrics to track changes after new features are introduced. As a result, it was possible to control metrics performance in the optimal area.
- Implemented a template for new repositories. As a result of this work, the time for creating new packages was cut in half.
- Implemented a package of helper-functions. As a result of this work, we got rid of code duplication in the main repository.

Optimax Dev | Front End Engineer

Aug 2018 - Dec 2019 | Remote work

- Implemented Google Analytics into the project to gather information on user actions, Dynamic Yield for personalization and A/B testing, Impact Radius for marketing programs. This allowed for better marketing campaigns, which significantly increased the company's profits.
- Rewrite over 2,000 files from Flow to TypeScript.
 It was necessary to do this, because the support for Flow had become much worse and there was no roadmap for further development of the technology. As a result of the transition to TS, we got better IDE support, easier adaptation when hired, because TS has a larger community.
- Implemented the first iteration of automatic E2E testing using Puppeteer. This reduced the regression testing time by several times.

Retail Rocket | Front End Engineer

Apr 2017 - Jul 2018 | Togliatti, Russia Federation

- Developed a template for email newsletters and for marketing widgets. This reduced the delivery time of new features to production by about 25%.
- Implemented a code review process, which reduced the number of bugs.
- Organized technical meetings for the frontend department. This allowed us to work with technical debt and make timely changes to the code base.

Gildiya PRO | Front End Engineer

Oct 2015 - Jul 2018 | Togliatti, Russia Federation

- Successfully launched 16 projects from various spheres, according to set deadlines.
- Developed an interface for the internal CMS, which allowed the company to offer a comprehensive solution to clients and improved the user experience for administrators using the CMS.
- Trained new Front End Engineer in the company.
 As a result, the frontend department grew from one person to eight. Teamwork allowed to increase the number of projects performed.

EDUCATION

Bachelor

Tolyatti State University, Applied Informatics, 2012 – 2016

GPA: 4.8 / 5.0

PROJECTS

Microblog on technical management | https://t.me/softlead [in Russian]

 I write notes after reading books, attending meetups, or from personal experience. The main task is to take notes on the material I've learned. I use this project as a journal of notes that I can refer to when mentoring in the future

Optimax Prime Podcast | https://redcircle.com/shows/optimax-prime [in Russian]

 Talking about IT with colleagues. With the podcast I train to speak and tell something on camera